so welcome everyone and to this lecture on graph conventional
networks um okay so this is the outline of the
lecture so first i will go quickly um on the
traditional coordinates the architecture and then i
will introduce graphs and i will also
remind definitions of convolutions to extend it to two graphs then i will
represent two classes of graph coordinates
the first one is what i call a spectral graph of let's and the second one is the
spatial graph problems and we'll talk a little bit about the
benchmarking graph neural networks and finally i will conclude
okay so let's start with the traditional covenant
so we all know coordinates are a breakthrough in computer vision
so when uh for the imagenet competition you know for the
image classification task um when combinate was used
uh they decreased by almost a factor two the error
of classification it was in 2012 and it was basically the end
of uh and crafting features and we shift the paradigm to and crafting learning
systems and now for this very specific task we
all know that we we go to superhuman performance
coordinates are also a breakthrough in speech
and natural language processing so a facebook when you want to translate you
are also using coordinates so contents are powerful
architectures to actually solve high dimensional
learning problems so we all know about the curse of dimensionality
so if you have an image let's say 1 000 by 1 000 pixels so it's you have 1
million variables an image can be seen as a point in a space of one million
dimensions and for each dimension if you sample by
using um by using 10 samples then you have a 10
to the power 1 million possible images so these spaces are
really huge and of course this is the question how
do you find the needle of information in this big
haystack so covenants are really powerful to extract
basically this this information of the best possible representation
of your of your image data to uh to solve problems
of course we don't know yet everything about
yeah we don't know yet everything about convnets so it's a kind of a miracle how
and how powerful how good they are and it's also quite exciting because
this opened many research areas to understand better and to develop new
architectures okay so when you use convnets you are
doing an assumption and the main assumption that you are
using is that your data so images videos speech is compositional
it means that it is form of patterns that are
local so you know this is the contribution of urban envision so
if you are at this layer for this neuron this neuron is going to be connected to
a few neurons in the previous layer and not all neurons okay so this is the
local reception field um assumption then you have also the
property of stationary stationarity so basically you have some
patterns um that are similar and that are
shared across your image domain okay so like
the yellow uh the yellow patches and the blue patches so they are they are all
similar to each other the last property is the article so you
make the assumption that your data is hierarchical in the sense that
your low level features are going to be
combined together to form a medium level features and then
this medium feature are going to be again
combined to each other to form higher and higher
abstract features so um so any convent work the same way
so the first part of the architecture is to extract
these conventional features and then the second part will be to solve your
specific task you know like classification
recommendation and so on and this is what we call you
know end-to-end systems and the first part
is to learn the features the second part is to solve your task
okay okay let's see more precisely what is the data domain
so if you have images volumes or videos basically so for example you
can see this image and if you zoom in this image
what you have is a 2d grid okay you have a 2d grid
this is the structure of of the domain of this image
and on the top of the of this grid you have some features
so for example in the case of a color image you will have
three features which are red green and blue
okay now if i'm looking at um natural language processing so like
sentences you will have a sequence of words and
basically you can see that you know as a 1d grid
and on the top of this grid for each node of the grid you will have a word
okay so a word can be represented by just
an integer for example the same also for speech
so what you see here is um the variation of the air pressure
and it's the same you know it's like you have the support is a one degree
and each for each node of the grid you will have
the the air pressure value okay which is which is a real number
so uh i think it's clear we all we all use all the time grids and grits
as you know as very strong regular special structure
and for this for this um for this structure this is good
because we mathematically we can define the confident operations like
convolution and pulling and also in practice it's very fast to do it
so everything everything is good now let's look at you know
new new data so for example social networks
okay so you want you want to do your task for example would be to do
advertisement or to also make recommendation so for a
social network i'm going to it's going to be clear but
i'm going to show you that if you take two notes so for example
you know you have this user let's say this user i and user j
and all the others you see that this is not a grid
okay so the connection the pairwise connection between all users
they do not form a grid they have a very special pattern of connections
and this is basically a graph okay so uh how do you define your graph you're
gonna see the connection between users so
if i user i user j are friends you're gonna have you know connection and then
for this you are going to use what we call an adjacency matrix
which is just going to record all the connection or non-connection um between
notes in your in your social networks okay and
on the top of your network uh for each user you
will have features so for example you have you know
messages you have images you have videos so they form you know some feature in a
d dimensional space in in neuroscience
in brain analysis for example we are really interesting to understand
uh you know the fundamental relationship between structure and function of the
brain so they are really um connected to each other and it's very
fundamental to understand that we also want for example to predict
uh neurodegenerative disease different stages of this disease
so that this is very important um for this we need to understand the brain and
the brain if you look at the brain the brain is uh
composed of what we call region of interest okay
and this region of interest if you take one region of interest
this region is not connected to all other regions in the brain actually they
are only connected to a few other regions
so it's it's and again you can see nothing to do with the grid
okay so this special connection uh between different region of the
brains they can be measured by the structural mri
signal and then you also have an adjacency matrix
between region i and region j and and here you have a strength of connection
which depends how many connections how many fibers do you have
to connect region iron region j okay and then on the top of this graph
so if you look at the region i then you will have activations you know
functional activation which is basically a time
series that you can see here and also we can record this
activation of the brain with a functional mri
okay the last example i want to show you is in quantum chemistry
so for example the task would be to design
new molecules for drugs and materials so so you see again the connection
between atoms has nothing to do with the grid
okay it really depends um how you're going to connect
your atoms and then you will have you know molecules
so uh so the connection between atoms they are called bond
um and you have you know different kind of bonds they can be a
single bond double bond aromatic bond and you have and you have also different
features like energy and many other features that you can use
from from chemistry um for for the node of the graph so they
are atoms and again you you you may have different features like the
type of atom if it is you know hydrogen if it is
hazard all this all these types you have also
the 3d coordinates you have the charge and so on you may have
multiple features okay so um and it's not uh
the list actually goes on to give you example
of graph graph domains so you also have you know computer graphics
with 3d meshes you also want maybe to analyze
transportation network and the density of of cars or maybe i don't know
trains you have also you know gene regulatory network
you have knowledge graphs um world relationships
you know users products where you want to do recommendations you have also seen
understanding you want to give more common sense to your computer
vision machine so you want to understand the relationship between between your
objects you also have you know for example if
you want to detect high energy physics particles so you
have characters and the captures are not you know structure as a regular grid so
for all this you see that there is a
denominator uh which is basically you can represent
all these um problems as graphs
okay and and here is the command setting i would
say the mathematical command setting for all these uh problems um
so the graphs uh let's let's call it uh g okay they are defined by three
entities so the first entity is going to be the set of vertices
so usually you are going to index the set of vertices from one to n
n is is the number of nodes in your in your graph
okay so for example this will be the index one
two three and so on then you will have you know the set of edges basically they
are the connections between um between the notes
and finally you will have the adjacency matrix a which will give you the
strength of the connection of your of your edge okay um
okay then you have graph features so for example for each node not i or not j
you will have some um some node features so it's
basically a vector of dimensionality dv okay
the same also it's possible that you can get
you can get h features and it's going to be a vector
of dimensionality d e so for example for molecules
the node feature maybe you know the atom type and the edge feature may be the
bond type to give you an example and finally you can have also some graph
feature okay for all for the whole graph you can have
some feature so again it's um it's a vector of dimensionality
dj and and in the case of of uh of
chemistry that that that may be the molecule energy
okay so this is um i would say the general definition of graphs
okay so now what i'm going to do is that i'm going to talk about convolution
and the question how do we extend convolution to graphs
okay so first let me remind you um the classical way to use convolutional
layer uh for grids when we use confinets for computer vision so
let's say um i have this image and or maybe this is some uh you know
hidden uh feature at layer l okay and i'm going to do the convolution with
uh some pattern or kernel um
that of course i will learn by back propagation and then i will get some
activation okay so this is the the features at the
next layer so to give you maybe some dimensionality
so for example n1 and 2 is going to be the number of pixels
in the x and y direction and d is the dimensionality
of uh of each pixel so if this is a color image the dimensionality is going
to be three for the three colors and if this
is like intermediate uh hidden feature maybe you
have 100 you know dimensions for the kernel usually you take small
kernels because you want to know the local reception field so that might be
you know three by three pixels kernel or five by one five by five and
of course you have d because you need to uh to respect the
dimensionality of your input uh after input features
okay so maybe for this one so you see that uh so you are going to convert this
image with this feature which is oriented in this
direction so you will basically identify uh you know
lines in in in this direction of the image
so that was just an example and we use padding right right now right so we have
the same dimensionality of the uh yes yes absolutely against padding so
you basically you don't reduce the size of your image
right yeah okay so so how do we mathematically define
convolution so the first definition is to do is to
see convolution as a template matching okay
so so template matching so here is the definition the mathematical definition
of a convolution so what you're going to do is that
you are going to take your template you are going to take your image
and then you are going to sum over um the index in the whole
image domain omega okay of wj and this is going to be a product
between vector w j and vector h i minus g
okay so this is the pure definition of convolution
and what we do usually in a in computer vision is that we don't take minus
we take plus okay and we call that because because when when we do that we
have the definition of correlation and this is this is you know because
it's more uh like it's it's exactly like template
matching okay so it doesn't change anything if you if you do i minus j or i
plus j in the learning sense because the only thing that you do is that you flip
up and down and left and right your uh your
your your kernel and when you learn you it doesn't change anything basically
okay but this is the definition of correlation so it's it's really a
template matching and then i'm going to take for the
notation i j okay so basically and yeah and something very
important that you have here is that you when when we do um convolutional
layers we are using kernel with compact support you know
like a 3x3 it's very small support when we do that we don't do the sum over
the whole domain the image domain we just do the sum over the
neighborhood of the node i okay and this is very
important it's very important because suddenly
the sum is not over the whole pixel it's just you know
um in the neighborhood and then the complexity of doing convolution is
actually um to the order of the number of nodes so
the number of pixels in your in your image so so the
the complete is quite easy to to compute so what you're going to do is that
you're going to take your uh your pattern you're going to slice
your pattern so it's going to be n slicing because n number of locations
and then you're gonna do you know a scalar product of three by three
elements and and you're gonna do you know um
um the vector a product of vectors of dimensionality so
you see the complexity of doing this operation is just
n times three times three times d so the completed is n
and and again everything can be done in parallel if you have a gpu the
computation that you are doing in this in this location is independent
to the competition that you're doing in this location so
everything is is linear complexity okay so doing that uh okay
so so at the end of the day if you want to do convolution with template matching
you're just going to compute this um scalar products between your template
and between uh your your image um i would say your image patch okay
um okay so something that is very important to see
in the case of the graph being grid so this is for standard convolution
in computer vision if you look at if you are looking at you
know your template which is here okay so you see that i'm going to give
some node ordering j1 g2 j3 and so on to g9
and this node ordering is actually very important
okay because for for all time i mean it's not i mean this this notes so for
example the node g3 will always be positioned at the same
location so it's always going to be at the top right
corner of the pattern okay so that's that's very important why
it's very important so let me go to the next slide
so why it's very important is so when i will do the convolution so the pattern
matching again i will take my my pattern and i
will slice the pattern over my image domain okay so that would
be maybe here and i put it here and and also this is
position i position i prime that i put here
so when i'm going to do the template matching between
the kernel and the image what i will do is that for
this index so the index g3 it will always match you know the
information in the image at this index here
okay so this is very important so you when you have a grid the node
ordering the node positioning is always the same whatever the position
in your image so when you do the template matching
between index g3 and this index here in the image you
always compare the same information you always compare the feature uh at the
top right corner uh of your pattern and the
type of corner of the image patch okay so this um this
uh you see this matching scores they are for the same information
okay so that's very important now let's look at what happened for graphs
okay so the question is can we extend this definition of template matching for
graphs and there are two main issues so the
first issue is basically on a graph you don't have
any uh ordering of your notes okay so on the graph you you have
no given position uh for your notes so let's say for example
i have this uh graph template okay so there are like four notes with
this connection and i have this uh vertex here the thing is for this
vertex i know nothing about the position the
only thing that i know is the index okay so maybe this is the
index number three for this one and then when i when if i
want to use the template machine definition what i'm going to do is that
i need to match you know this uh index with other index uh
in the graph domain so this is my graph and let's say this is for
the node i and they are the neighbors of the node i so
for this neighbor this is the index the same index j3
but here i mean how can i match you know this information with this
information when i do not know if they match to it they
mature to each other because on the graph you don't have any
ordering of your notes you don't know if it's not it's for the
top right corner of any information you don't know that
so on the graph you have no notion of where is the up where is the down where
is the right where is the left okay so when you do this matching
between uh this feature vector and this picture
vector actually this matching usually generally has no meaning okay you
you you don't know what you compare to each other okay
and again the index is completely arbitrary
okay so you can have the value 3 here but it can be here
the value number 2 or value number 12. you you don't have
this is this is not you know any good information
so basically because you don't have any ordering of your notes on graphs
you cannot choose the definition of template matching
you cannot use that directly so we need to do something else
okay the second issue with template matching for graphs
is what happens if um the number of nodes in your template
does not match the number of nodes you know uh
in your in your graph so for example here i have four nodes
here i have four nodes fine maybe i can find a way to compare
the two in the two sets of of nodes but here i have
uh i have seven nodes so how i'm going to compare seven nodes to four nodes
so that's also you know an open issue okay so the third mathematical
definition was to use template matching to define convolution
now the second definition is to use the convolution the convolution theorem
so the convolution theorem from um from fourier is basically the fourier
transform of the convolution of two functions
is the pointwise product of the fourier transform this is what you see here
okay so the fourier transform of the convolution of
a function w and function h is the fourier transform of f
and point twice multiplication the fourier transform of h then if you do
the inverse for your transform you go back to your to your convolution
so nice okay we have a very um nice formula to
do the convolution of w and h and but the thing is in the general
case doing the fourier transform is n square
complexity we come back to that however if you if your domain uh like
uh like the image grid has some very particular structure
then you can reduce the complexity to n log n uh by using you know
uh fast fourier transform okay so the question is
can we extend this definition of uh of convolution theorem to graphs
so the question is how do we redefine a fourier transform
for four graphs okay and and the thing is how to make it fast
okay so remember that in the case of uh of template matching
uh we have linear complexity so how do we
have a fast spectral convolution in linear time
for compact kernels so that's that's the two open question
okay so basically we are going to use these two definitions
of convolution to uh design two classes of graph neural network so the
this will be the template machine will be for the spatial graph cornets
and the conversion rotary i'm going to use that for the spectral graph net and
this is the next the next part that i'm going to talk
about now okay so let's talk about
how we do spectral convolution okay so i there is a book that i like very
much uh which is the book of uh fan chung
which is a spectrograph theory so there is
everything in nice like harmonic analysis graphery combinatorial
problems and optimization so i really recommend you know people to
read the books they want to know more and a lot more
about about these these questions so how do we perform
spectral convolution so we are going to use four steps so the
first step will be to do would be to define graph application
second step will be to define fourier functions then
we will do fourier transform and eventually
convolution theorem okay
so the what is the graph location so the graph calculation
this is the core operator in spectral graph theory okay
so remember how we define a graph we have a set of vertices
a set of edges and then we have the adjacency matrix
so if the graph has n vertices the adjacency matrix
is a n by n matrix so we are going simply to define the
laplacian which is also going to be an n by n matrix to be
the identity minus the adjacency matrix and we are
going to normalize the adjacency matrix by using
the degree of each node so d is basically a diagonal matrix
and the diagonal each element of the diagonal is basically the degree of the
node okay so we are doing and this is called
the normalized location okay so this is i would say this is by
default the definition of uh laplacian that we use for for graphs
so we can interpret uh this uh this operator
so the laplacian is this combination so the a was that matrix with basically all
zeros and the one was representing the
connection between edges right um yes so
uh for facebook for example i would say that this is exactly the definition so
if not a user i is a friend with a user j then you will
have adjacency matrix value will be i j equal
to one and if two users are not friends
then you will get the value zero but sometimes you have a real value
for a for example for the for the brain connectivity graph
the value of aij is the degree of connection between the two regions so
basically what we say the number of fibers that connect
region i and region j so that can be binary that can be also a continuous
value and also this is symmetric if it's non
oriented graph otherwise yes so yeah for
usually it is symmetric uh and you want you want the symmetry for for
mathematical reasons um but you may have some not so here
this is the normalized elevation but if you have the random walk
laplacian then this is non-symmetric okay
so it's um it's it's different definition of the application so
in the case of laplacian it's very interesting so in the continuous setting
you have only one definition for the application this is called the laplace
beltrami operator in the discrete setting you have
multiple definitions you can do your own definition of the application depending
on on the assumptions that that you are going to use i
understand thank you okay so we can interpret the
application so the application is nothing else than a measure of
smoothness of a function on a on a graph
so this is nothing else then you you see you see so i'm doing the elaboration
that i reply to a function h okay on the graph and i'm looking at
what happened at the vertex i and if i expand this
definition i will have the value of h i minus
the mean value of the neighborhood okay so basically if your signal is smooth
you know if it doesn't vary much then this difference will be very small
but if your signal you know there is a lot
it oscillates a lot then the difference will be very
high so the laplacian is nothing else and a measure of smoothness of function
on a on a on a graph okay all right so
now let's define fourier functions so let's let's take the
laplacian matrix and let's do a little bit of linear algebra
let's do eigen decomposition of the graph operation
so when you do eigen decomposition you will have the
you will you are going to factorize your laplacian matrix
into three matrices so you have a phi transpose
lambda and five so this matrix five of the size n by n actually
uh have the what are the laplacian eigenvectors
okay for each column and the laplacian eigenvectors
they are called the fourier functions okay the famous fourier functions
and of course this is an orthonormal basis
um so when you do the the product between two bases you will get one
if they are the same and then you get zero if they are orthogonal
if they are different this is also an invertible matrix this
guy so this matrix this is the diagonal matrix of the laplacian
eigenvalues so lambda 1 to number n
and and we know that for the normalized application
that these values are bonded between zero and between
two so this is the maximum value that you can get this guy
the laplacian eigenvalues they are known as the spectrum
of the graph okay so if you take a graph here you have 27
nodes if i compute the laplacian eigenvalues and if i put them
i have a signature of the graph which is called the spectrum of the graph
okay that which would be different for each each graph
okay and here you have okay this is what i say so this is
doing um again decomposition so if you take your
laplacian matrix and you apply to a vector
phi of k then you will get the eigenvalue lambda k times the same
vector phi of k okay so this is the definition
of the um eigen decomposition okay so you see that
fourier functions they are nothing else than
the laplacian eigenvectors okay let me illustrate uh these uh
fourier functions so we actually we already know uh for your functions
uh if you if you take the greater for example you take here a one degree
and you compute the fourier functions so you so you will get a phi
zero okay then you will get phi one which is this one which is smooth phi
two which is less a little less mousse and
phi 3 and so on and so on so this is well known this is the cosine function
and the semi-zoids and we use that you know for
for image compression so if we take an image and we project the image
on the fourier functions then the image is going to be the the transformation is
going to be sparse so you only keep you know the highest
coefficient and you can do compression so this is something that we've used for
a very long time for for graph for the graph
domain this is this is quite interesting so you see that this is a graph and i'm
computing here the the first uh four uh you know fourier
function of the graphs so you see for phi one uh you still have
oscillations you know between positive and negative
value the same with positive and negative value and and here as well
um what is interesting is that this oscillation
uh depends on the topology of the graph okay
so so it's related to the to the geometry of the graph like communities
like hubs and so on and we know that uh so for example
if you want to capture k communities on graph
uh a very good algorithm is to apply k-means on the first key
fourier functions if you do that you have something that we call spectrograph
theory and it's it's a it's a huge literature
uh and and if you want to know more about
this there is this very nice tutorial by van looks pro
about about spectrograph clustering and using all these notions of fourier
functions okay okay now let me introduce you
a fourier transform okay so for this i'm going to
do the fourier series for your series if is nothing else
then you take a function h defined on your graph
and then you are going to decompose this function using the fourier function
okay so i take my function h i project my function
h on each fourier function phi of k and i will get you know
this coefficient of this fourier series it's going to be a scalar
multiply by my function phi of k okay of the time and
n by one of the size and n by one okay so and doing that you know
just projecting my function on the fourier functions
give me the fourier transform okay so the fourier transform
is is just you know the coefficient of the fourier series nothing else
okay then h you know is basically a linear combination of the fourier
transform times the the fourier functions okay i can
rewrite everything in matrix vector
representation and these guys so doing the um phi
times the the fourier transform this is actually the inverse for your transform
okay so let me summarize this if i do if i project h on the fourier
functions i will have the fourier transform okay so i'm taking
the matrix of the fourier functions and multiply by h so this is n by
n by n this is n by one so this is n by one
okay uh and now if i do inverse fourier transform of the fourier
transform okay so i would have phi of um
fourier transform of h and this guy is here
okay so i just put phi transpose h and we know that um the the basis
is orthonormal so this guy is actually identity function
that am sorry identity matrix okay so this is energy matrix so i come back to
h so so the inverse for your transform is is of of the fourier transform is h
obviously okay so one thing that you can observe is that
the fourier transform and the inverse fourier transform
can be done in one line of code okay you just take
your vector h you multiply by this matrix and that's it
and the same also to do the inverse for your transform you take your your signal
and you multiply by this matrix so it's basically just linear operations
uh just multiplying a matrix by a vector and this is how you do fourier
transforming inversely transform on graphs
okay now let's let's do the convolution theorem
so again the convolution theorem the fourier transform
the fourier transform of your um the free transform of the convolution
is is going to be the pointwise product of the fourier transform of
each signal okay so let's say i have um w convolution h uh so i'm going
first to do the fourier transform of w then
this is going to be a vector of the size n by one
then i'm going to multiply point twice by another vector which is the fourier
transform of h okay so how do we get the free
transform just by doing phi transpose w and phi transpose h and
then i'm going to do the inverse fourier transform to come
to go back to the spatial domain so i just multiplied by the matrix five
okay and by n so this is what i write here
okay i have phi i have um w hat which is a fourier transform and i
have this this i'm going to change it i'm going to
change it to this line what is this line um shouldn't there be a phi transpose
before w hat sorry shouldn't there be a 5's transpose
before w hat no the inverse fourier transform is fine
okay so you do phi and you multiply by the
fourier transform which is a phi transpose w
which i call hat w so i'm going i'm going to use that a lot
uh i will come back to this and then here you have the fourier
transform of h which is just phi transpose h which is here
okay so this guy um okay this guy is actually what we call
the spectral function okay the spectral filter so this guy is
a vector of n by one okay and i'm writing i'm writing here uh
this vector here so you see this is a vector of uh n
elements and this is actually the spectral
function which is um evaluated
at the at the uh at the eigenvalue lambda 1 which is here so this is this
point here then you have a w uh hat
number two which is this this value here and so on and so on okay
and then i'm going to rewrite this you know i'm going to put this
uh in a diagonal okay so i will do diagonal of
this vector so this will create a matrix of the size
n by n okay and i'm putting this guy back here
so i'm going to change the the point twice multiplication of this vector n by
one and this vector by one by the matrix vector
multiplication and it's going to be the same right this
is a diagonal matrix which contains this guy
multiply multiply by this by this vector so this it's exactly the same these two
lines but what i want to do that because i want to get rid of the
parenthesis okay so i don't have the parenthesis anymore
and i have just you know matrix matrix multiplication
okay so this is this is what i get um then i'm going to do something is
that we know that when you apply a function
on the eigenvalues okay if you have some orthogonal basis
then you can put it inside you can put it inside and this is what i do here
i put phi and phi transpose inside and this guy is precisely the definition
of the application okay the operation uh when i do the
again the composition is phi launder file transpose
okay um then so what i have is basically the spectral
function that i applied to the application uh
operator and this is n by n uh matrix
and applied to the vector n by one so at the end i would get
an n by one vector okay so you see that if you want to do so it's important now
so if you want to do a convolution of two functions on graph
w and h what you're going to do is that you're
going to take the spectral function of w you will apply it
to the uh to the laplacian and then you
multiply by h okay this is the definition of uh
of spectral convolution okay and and the thing is
this is very expensive uh in practice to do it why it is expensive
it's because the matrix phi is a full matrix okay it contains uh
the n uh the n um fourier functions and they are not zero okay so it's a
dense matrix and you are going to pay the price of n square
and you don't have any fft because the thing you don't have any fft
for uh for general graph okay so this is a
this is this is a lot and why it is a lot because n remember
and this is the number of nodes in your domain
so if you have um if you have a big graph for example if you have
uh the web the web has you know billions of nodes n is equal to the billions so
you need to do b and square which is going to be a huge
computation to do so you cannot really do it
can i summarize so h is going to be a function defined
over every vertex in your graph right uh and w instead is going to be like a
kernel as well or is he but w is going to be a function
like this so w is a spectral function w hat
is the spectral function so you are working
in the frequency space in the frequency space you are working with this
what this is this is a spectral function so for example
if you if you know image processing a little bit so for example if you want to
do image denoising if you want to do image denoising what
you what you know is that you know that the noise is usually in
the high frequency part of your image of your signal so what you
can do is that you can design a spectral filter
which is going to be zero for the high frequency and you are going
to preserve you know the low frequency to preserve
your your geometry so this is just you know doing filtering
of the frequencies you know contain in your signal
okay okay but the wd without the hat would be still a small guy right would
be a small uh filter exactly so w without hat
is the special filter yeah the small one right which is exactly so
exactly so if you have the grid w will be
you know a three by three uh a three by three you know the
patch for example now i see okay okay okay
thanks yeah sure um so in the context of graph uh so it's it's
a small property um to know is that you don't have any
shifting values um so if you have a grid and if you are
using the convolutional um theorem uh to to move around you know
your function for example the function is aggression here on the grid you are
not going to change the shape of your function
but on a graph because you have you know uh irregular structure
if you move around your gaussian then you will have different shapes
okay so this is something that that you lose when you go
to graphs but in practice actually it has absolutely no effect so it's not
really important it's just a mathematical property that you lose
when you go to graphs okay there is another question there is
another question i got here so can you ask can you remind us what is
actually the overall goal here what is the goal of defining these
convolutions or the spectral correspondence over these graphs i think
uh maybe it's not yeah if we can remind everyone it's going to be
yeah so so what i'm trying the the goal of the lecture
is to define a convolutional graph convolutional nets okay
so i need to redefine a convolution in the case of graphs and there are two
ways to define convolutions uh you can do convolution with template
matching or you can do convolution with a graph spectral theory
so what i'm doing here um i'm i'm redefining convolution in the case of
spectral theory and then i'm going to use this definition
of convolution to define graph convolutional nets so my goal is
just to define convolution in the case of graphs
so i can i can i can design a graph convolutional nodes okay sounds great
okay so let's go to um now okay so now the first part was okay i defined a
spectral convolution now i'm going to use
spectral convolution to define gcn okay okay so the first model
what i call vanilla spectral gcn was introduced
actually by januka and his collaborators so
john brenner zahamba and archer slam in 2014 i think it was for
the first uh iqr conference um and what they did
they did you know the the simple uh idea to do
okay let's let's let's uh you know define a graph uh spectral convolutional
layer so we know what is you know a standard
convolutional layer so you you this is the activation at the next layer
a plus one this is your non-linear activation so this is for example
um and then i'm going to do the spatial filter so
the template wl convolution by hm okay so this is
in the special domain uh the graph domain
and then i'm going to do that and remember that what i just defined
so doing this convolution in the spectral domain it's just doing that
okay so this is the spectral filter apply to the application and then you
multiply by hl okay so this guy is is a
i can decompose this guy i will get the fourier
matrix times the spectral function that i apply to the
eigenvalues uh phi transpose hm okay and and and this is my uh this is
my spectral filter okay so i do not work directly here okay
i work directly here and and here the thing that i'm going to
learn i'm going to actually to learn this
function w hat number one so i'm going to learn
um the spectral filter and i'm going to learn it by back propagation
okay so i don't need to um you know handcraft the the the spectral
filter i don't need to do that this will be learned by by propagation
so that was really a great idea to do it and this was the
first spectral technique but but it has some limitations so the
first limitation is that you don't have any guarantee of special localization of
filters uh so remember that uh what we want we
want to have the local reception field because it's it's a very good property
to be able to extract uh you know multi-scale um multiscale
feature which is scale patterns from from your signal so you don't have
you don't have this guarantee the second thing is that how many
parameters do you need to learn so you need to learn n parameters
okay you need to learn this w hat number one to
do when you have number n so it's n parameters so
if again if the graph is is large like uh like like the the web you know
or facebook then this is gonna be billions uh of
parameters to learn and this is for each layer so it's gonna
be really huge and again the learning complexity is going to be n square
because your phi is a dense matrix so so we need to improve this okay so
so uh so jan and his collaborator so they improve
the improved true properties so the first property was
okay how do we get localized spatial filters okay so for this
what what they propose is to um okay to get
um localized special filter so you want something which is localized
uh what you need to do is to uh compute smooth spectral filters something very
smooth like this okay so why do you why do you want
smooth spectral filter it's because if you are smooth in the
frequency space then you are going to be localized in
the space domain okay so this is in physics you know the
eisenberg's entity principle and you can see that you know with the
personal identity if let's let's say that k is equal to
one if k is equal to one you have the first derivative of
uh of the spectral function so if you want this to be
small okay so you're going to have a smooth function
and for k equal to one you see here is this is going to be the variance
of your spatial filter so if this is small
if the variance is small it means that you're gonna have a small
you're going to have a special filter with a small compact
support okay so if you are smooth in the frequency space you're going to
be localized in the spatial space okay so you need
smoothness how do you get smoothness for spectral feature so you
can also think about the uh the transform of the delta of the
dirac right so we if we have a delta in the iraq in the in
the time domain then in the frequency we're going to have
basically a flat a completely flat transform right
so there's another maybe a way to see uh if someone doesn't
quite know the parseval identity yeah exactly
right um and so so how do you get a smooth spectral filter
so the idea is okay we can simply decompose
you know the spectral filter to be a linear combination
of smooth kernels okay so the smooth kernel was chosen to be
splines because splines are nice they are you
know with compact support and they are smooth and basically the
idea is okay now let's learn a vector of k coefficient uh and this is
the case muscular node okay and you learn this coefficient by
by propagation but suddenly you know everything is nice because you have
locality localization in space and the number of parameters that you're
going to learn is going to be key parameters so here for example let's
say it's nine okay remember that before uh in the case
of um of convolution so you have a three by
three which is which is nine parameters so that can be the same you can have
nine parameters to learn you're gonna you're gonna learn
a combination of nine spline functions and and that's it so you have a constant
number of parameters to learn earlier so this is nice but we still have you
know the the phi matrix so we the learning
complexity is still quadratic okay
okay so so the question is um how do we learn
in linear time okay so how do we learn uh with respect to the to the graph size
n so the problem of the quadratic complexity
comes from directly from the use of the laplacian again vectors
okay so you see that uh the thing that is that is annoying
uh in this spectral convolution is not this diagonal matrix
it's not this vector it's this guy okay this is this is the phi
matrix because it's a full matrix right it's a dense matrix
and and then and then it's n square number of elements so this is the price
that we need to pay so we know that if we want to avoid
the quadratic complexity we need to avoid the eigen decomposition okay
um and and okay so we can avoid organic position but simply directly
learn function of the application okay so this is what what we proposed in
2007 2016. so the spectral
function is just going to be you know a monomial
function of the application that's it so we just have a sum
of some parameters that we learned by by propagation
w k and laplacian to the power of k okay so so when we do that
uh first there is something uh which is which is good is that
uh we're gonna have filters that are exactly localized
in a k-hop support okay so if we have the application to the power k
the spectral um i mean the spatial filters
will be exactly localized in the support of k-hop
so what is the what is the one hope neighbor
neighborhood so let's say for example you have this
graph and here i'm going to put a heat source so the value is going to be 1
at this node and 0 for all other nodes if i apply the application to this heat
source then the signal the support of the signal is going to be
increased by one hop so every uh basically every node
that can be reached by one jump okay that you do that
and and if you do two jumps from this you will
you will reach the the second hop uh neighborhood which is your range uh
the orange nodes here okay so if you apply the
application uh two times this is gonna be the support okay if you
apply the application k times then you will have the support of k-hops
so you you exactly uh control the the size of your spatial
filters okay so that that was the first point
the second point let me show you that you get uh
learning complexity okay so so again you have your convolution wh
you have your spectral convolution definition i'm using here
as a spectral convolution um monomials of the of the application and then i'm
going to replace this guy so the laplacian power of k times the
vector h by the vector x
k okay and x k is actually given by your recursive equation
okay so recursive is always good right so it's given by this recursive equation
which is the application times the vector
xk minus one and the x k equal to zero is simply the original uh function h
okay so so when i do that you see that this sequence
x of k is generated by multiplying a matrix
so the operation and the vector x k minus 1.
so the complexity of doing that is the number of edges
okay and you do it that you know k times so number of edges
times k and the thing is uh for real graph
real world graphs um basically they are all sparse
okay because sparsity is structure so remember for example for
um for for the web the web has a billions of of web pages but for each
webpage it is in average connected to 50 other
webpage so comparing 50 to 1 billion is nothing
so usually and the same also for the brain the brain it's very highly sparse
the same also for uh transport networks so everything
every natural graph is usually sparse because sparsity is structure
okay so so the number of edges is you know some value times n so at the
end of the day uh you have linear complexity uh because
for for sparse real world graphs okay um okay so and you see here is that i'm
using the laplacian and i never do any eigen decomposition
of the elaboration okay um and there is so there is a bit
of um of confusion that sometimes i see
is that so i call this spectral uh you know gcn
but this is this might be misguided because i don't do
any spectral uh operations like you know i don't use any either again the
composition with the application we i don't have any eigenvectors again
values so so at the end of the day even if i use
you know the spectral theory to define this gcn um
at the end of the day the computation are all done in the special domain using
the operation okay i don't use any i don't choose the
spectral domain for the computation i use i do
everything in the special domain so even we call that spectral gcn
we don't choose you know in practice and the spectral
uh decomposition so just just one one one command
okay and the last like the last comment i want to do is that so graph
conditional layers again this is just linear operations so you just multiply a
vector a matrix by a vector so you're just
doing in operation so this is gpu friendly
the issue um is that here you are doing sparse linear algebra and the existing
gpu are not optimized for that so this is i
think one of the limitations today for graph neural
networks we need to have specialized eyewear for graph neural networks we
need to have hardware that adapt uh to the to the sparsity
uh of of these operations and we don't have this today so
uh if we want this to to to get far very far with graphene network we need
to have this this uh this specialized hardware
what about tpus do you know whether tpus can handle that's the same that's the
same they are optimized for uh full uh you know linear
operations like full matrices uh they're
specialized for that but if you if you want to do sparse
linear algebra you need specialized hardware to do that
gotcha thanks yeah
okay so how do we implement um how do we implement this and so for
example we have a signal we have a function defined on the on the
graph so n is the number of vertices of your graph and d is the
dimensionality uh of uh of the feature right so for
each node you have a feature a vector of d
dimension okay so how we do that so we have x k
and what we do is that we are just going to uh do a
shape stuff to do just linear operations so
x k are going to be arranged in a matrix you know um x bar which is of the size
of k times nd okay so we just reshape you
know this xk to be 1 times nd and
and we have k times nd and then we multiply this
by the vector that we will learn by back propagation which is of the size k by
one okay we do that the operation will give
you one times nd you reshape and you get n times d
so this is how how i implement it you know
with pi torch or tensorflow that would be the same
and this is how you do this spectral convolution
so again the properties is that filters are exactly localized
you have a constant number of parameters to learn so this is a key
you know this is this is this k a parameters that you need to learn by
back propagation you have a learning complexity a linear
learning complexity but the thing uh which uh which is not
good is that um here i'm using monomial um basis
okay so i'm using uh laplacian to the power zero laplacian to the power one
power two power three and so on okay this is what i use here
and the thing is monomial bases are unstable for
uh for for optimization because this basis
you know is not too orthogonal so if you change one coefficient then
you are going to change the approximation of your
function so you need orthogonality if you want to learn
with stability okay so then you can use your favorite you know
orthonormal basis but your favorite orthonormal
basis must have a recursive equation okay so
this is the only thing that that that you that you need you need
your autonomous basis to to have a relationship equation because this is
the key to have the linear complexity so we use
a chebychev polynomials so this is uh something very
well known in signal processing um so we are going to approximate you
know the spectral convolution uh with the cheby uh jb chef chebyshev
function the chef functions apply to h again can
be represented by xk and xk is given by this recursive
equation okay so it's a little more complex than
before but in practice this is just doing again
multiplication of uh your elaboration times the vec one
vector okay at the end of the day the the
complexity is still linear you don't change anything
um and this time you have stability during your during the learning process
okay so what we did we did the sanity check with mnist
um so and you see that so this is the number
of vertices so so for mnist the the graph is the standard grid
okay we use the k-nearest neighbor grid to do that
and you see that um you have linear complexity okay this is the
number of vertices and and and you have this
number of of uh you have the linear complexity so this is good
for the accuracy you get to see 99 percent of accuracy
compared to the standard n5 okay so chad net uh social
is basically combat for arbitrary graph and we have the same linear
learning complexity of course um the complexity constant is much larger than
than the standard uh than the standard net
so it's something like 20 or 30. so it's much much smaller
to learn on this but you get you know covenant for any arbitrary graph
so that's that's uh that's what you mean another limitation is
um it's an isotropic model so so let me talk a little bit about i
uh isotropy versus anisotropy so if you look at you know the standard
complex then you are going to produce anisotropic filters like this one okay
so you see that this filter is an isotropic
it goes in this direction okay and we can get anisotropic
filters with standard coordinates because we are using
a grid and on a grid we have you know a directional we have directions we know
where is the up where is down where is left where is
right right remember that we know the ordering of uh of the nodes
on on the grid we know that but this is different for graphs
we don't have any notion of direction we we don't know where is the
where is up where is down where is left or is right
so the thing the only thing that we can do at this point
is that we can only compute isotropic filters
isotropic filters means that the value of the filter
will be the same you know for in in all directions
uh for for for four cycles okay for for cycles of the same radius
okay so this is uh this is what we can get we
can only get isotropic filters when we use a chip net
because we have no notion of direction on arbitrary graphs
and i will come back to that i will come back to the isotropy versus anisotropy
a bit later okay so what we what we did also is to
uh very quickly i don't i don't have the time now oh wow the time is uh so i need
to speed up a little bit so we did we did expand also this um
spectral convolution from one graph to multiple graphs so you can
do that you know it's like extending from 1d signal processing to
2d image processing so extension is mathematically
straightforward to do and we did that you know for for
example for recommender systems because we have users of movies and
users of graphs so with that we also as i said before is
that you can use your favorite uh you know orthogonal uh polynomial
basis uh so we use uh kylie nets because uh
chebychev are unstable to localize frequency bands of interest which are
basically the graph communities we use that something a
more powerful you know more powerful spectral functions
okay which is kind of neat okay so now let me go to the
to the to this class of uh graph continents that i call
special graphs and then for this class i'm going back to the template matching
uh you know definition of convolution so how we do clamping matching for graphs
so remember that um the main issue um the main issue when you want to do
template matching for graph is that you you don't have any node ordering or
positioning for your template okay uh
we don't have any positioning so basically with the only thing that we
have we have the the index of the notes and that's it but
the index is not enough to match you know information between
between nodes um so how can we design
template matching to be invariant to node reparametrization
okay so you have a graph this index of the node
is maybe let's say six but it's completely arbitrary i can have an
index with the number 122 for example so i want to be able to
do template matching independently of the
index of this node okay so how i do that so
the simplest thing you can do is actually to
have only one uh you know template vector to do the matching this is
so you don't have you know w j1 wg2 wj3 you don't have this you just have one
vector w and you are doing the matching of this
vector with all other you know feature
on your on your graph okay this is the simplest
template feature matching you can do which is environment by node
reparameterization and actually this property is going to
be used for most graph neural networks today
okay so here is the mathematical definition
um so i'm just going to do the the product between uh the template
vector w at layer l so this is the d by one
and and i have the vector at node j which is also the dimensionality d by
one okay i will get to scalar so here this is only for one feature
of course you will have to get more features so instead of having
a vector d by one you're going to use a matrix
d by d so this way you can get you know d features for each node i okay
and then i so this is the the representation at
a node i i can put everything in vector representation
okay this is my um this is my activation at layer a plus one it is defined on
on the graph of m vertices and it has d dimensions
okay and and this can be rewritten as uh the adjacency matrix a so this is
n by n matrix this is my activation at the layer
l so this is the n by d uh you know matrix and this is the the template
that i'm going to learn by back propagation of the size d by d
okay so you do you do this product you get n by d
okay so based on this template matching of graph now i'm going to define
uh two classes of uh spatial gcn which are the isotropy gcn
and the anisotropy gcn so let's start with the isotropic gcn
so this is act actually as a as quite some history
okay so uh the simplest formulation of special gcn was introduced by
uh scarcely and his co-author so he was in 2009 before the deep learning
revolution and then more recently by uh thomas
keith maxwelling um and also saiyan suk bata
and archer slam and rob fergus in 2016. so this is actually um this graph neural
networks of what they call the vennina graph combination nets okay this is
exactly the same definition that i have before just here i put you know the gb
matrix in such a way that i have the mean value
okay i just do the mean value over the neighborhood okay but this is
exactly the the equation that i used before okay
um and you see that so this equation is um it can handle
uh absence of no ordering so this is completely invariant to another or
parametrization so again if this index is maybe six and i change to be 122 is
not going to change anything in the computation of the of h
at the next layer it's not going to change anything you can also deal with
a neighborhood of different sizes okay you don't care if you have
a neighborhood of four nodes or neighborhood of 10 nodes it's not going
to change or one or not it's going to change anything
you have the local reception field by design with graph neural network you
just need to look at the neighbors and and that's it so it's given to you
you have weight sharing okay you have weight sharing it means
that for for all features you are going to use the
same w whatever the position on the graph
okay so this is a convolution property um this formulation is also independent
of the graph size because all operations are done locally
okay you just use you know local information
for the next from the next layer so you can have a graph of 10 knots or you can
have a graph a graph of 10 billion nodes it doesn't
care so you can do also everything in parallel
and but this is limited to isotropic capability so the w
is the same for all neighbors so it's again it's an isotropic
model it's going to give the same value for all neighbors okay but at the end of
the day this model can be represented by this
figure so um this uh
so the activation at the next layer is basically a function
of the activation at the current layer at
uh index at at the node i and the neighborhood of the node i okay
and the only thing that we're going to do basically uh
is to change the function the instantiation of
of the function and then you will get all family of graph
neural network by just you know deciding a different function here but
everything is based on this equation so again
you have your your your core node and then you have your neighborhood
to decide what will be the activation at the next layer
okay so i'm running out of time so i'm not going to take too much time on this
but what you can show is that this previous
vernier gcn i just showed you is actually a
simplification of chebnet so if you truncate the expansion of
chain by using the first two chef function that at the end you end up
with the same equation so so this is this is the relationship
uh okay so one interesting uh gcn is graph sage
that was introduced by william in turn lee and yuri leskovek so let's say for
let's let's go back to the vanilla gcn so and let's suppose that the adjacency
matrix has a value one for for for the edges
okay so i have this equation so the thing is for this equation i'm
going to treat you know the central vertex i
and the neighborhood with the same template weight
okay but i can differentiate that you know i can have a template
for the central node w1 and i can have a template
for the one hope neighborhood okay by doing that
you improve already a lot you know your the performance of your official graph
neural networks so you go from here to here so you have
again um some templates for the central node
and the template for for the neighborhood
okay but this is still an isotropic uh isotopic gcn okay because you are
treating all the neighbors with the same weight
uh here this is the mean but you can change you can take the sum you can also
take the max you can take also something more
elaborated like lstm okay now more recently people um try to
improve the uh the theoretical understanding
of uh of gcn so there was um the graph isomorphous i i think isomorphism
networks are introduced by yuri leskovec in 2018 so the idea is can we design an
architecture that can differentiate graphs that are not
isomorphic so you know isomorphic is basically a measure of equivalence
between between graphs so these two graphs are isomorphic to each other
and of course you want to treat them the same way but if you are not isomorphic
you want especially to treat them in a different way okay
so so there was um a graph neural network uh
based on this one on this on this definition but this is still an
isotropic gcn okay
so so now i'm going to talk about anisotropic gcn so again
um again so i go back to what i said before is that standard cornet can
produce uh isotropic filters because there is a
notion of directions on grids okay so you have this um
isotropic filter in this direction uh gcn like a chemnet kylie net veneer gcn
graph sage and gene they compute isotropic filters so you
have this kind of filters that you learn during the
process but they are they are isotropic but we know that isotropy is
very powerful right so um how do we get back
anesthotropine graphene our networks so you can you can get an isotropic
naturally for example if you have edge features um
for like if you're taking chemistry molecules you know that
the bond features can be different they can be you know single double aromatic
bonds so naturally you would get an isotropic
you know gcm and again if we want to
design um a mechanism for isotropy we want this mechanism to be independent
with respect to the node parametrization so to do that
we can use for example h degrees and so that was proposed by monet edge gate
that we propose um in getty gcn or attention mechanism
uh in get and the idea is what what i put
here as an illustration okay so um here you're going to treat
your neighbors in the same way okay so with the same
template but you want you want to treat your
neighbors in a different way right if this is j1 you want a different
weight than if it was for j2 what do you want that is for example if
you want to analyze graphs you know that you have
communities of people um which are different for example i
don't know if it is politics you have republicans and democrats
so you don't want to know to have the the same analysis for for the same group
of people so you want anisotropy for graph that
that's quite important okay so the first model uh who deal with
endoscopy was monette so he was introduced by federico monty
michael bronstein and their co-author and the idea was to do
was to use gmm so gaussian mixture model and to learn the parameters of the
gaussian mixture so here they have k washington model and
they learn the parameters by using the degree
of uh of the graph um then there is also gat so uh it was
developed by peter velikovic and uh joshua banjo and
their co-author was basically to use the attention
mechanism developed by jimmy badeno yeshua banjo
to introduce anisotropy in the neighborhood allegation function
okay and so this is this is what you see here
so you have um you're going to concatenate so it's a multi-head
um wiki and architecture and here you have uh
this weight which are basically the soft max
um on the neighborhood okay you do the soft max on the neighborhood so
some info some um some notes will be more important than the others
you know by given by soft softmax what we use um with um thomas laurent um
and me in 2017 we we use a simple uh age uh getting mechanism which is which
is which is you know what a sort of soft
attention process compared to the sparse attention
mechanism of your show avenger and and here what we did also we use
edge feature explicitly and this actually recently we discovered
that this is very important for edge prediction task if you have explicit
explanation task this is important to keep it okay
so so this is the model that we used uh okay um
then okay so if i take transformer and if i if i
write down the equation of the graph version of transformer this is
that i would get okay so you recognize here the value
here you have the query here you have the key and here you have the softmax
but the softmax is done in the neighborhood in one hot neighborhood
okay that would be this and here i'm going to make um
um a connection with a transformer of uh vesmani and and their and his
collaborators so what is a transformer so a standard
transformer is actually a special case of uh graph
conventional nets when the graph is fully connected okay
so this is a fully connected graph so you
take any node i and this node is going to be connected
to all other nodes in your graph and included itself okay so
if you look at this equation the equation i just wrote before
you know if the the neighborhood uh is this time not the one hop
neighborhood but the whole graph then you will get you know uh the
standard equation that if if you do nlp and and transformer you
will recognize directly okay we saw this last week so
just exactly so that's that's a nice connect and that's a
transition so so you see you have the concatenation so this is multi-head you
have the softmax the query the key and the value and then
you have the weight uh for the meeting head so and the only
thing that i do here mathematically just having the neighborhood
uh that that use you know all connection and when i do that so there is the
question so what does it mean to do you know graph convolutional nets
for fully connected graphs and i think in this case
it becomes less useful to talk about graphs because when you when you have
each data connected to all other data then you don't have any more you know
specific graph structure because the graph which is what is
really interesting is graph is the sparsity structure
right like the brain connectivity like uh you know
the social networks what is interesting is not everything to be connected to
each other it's only to have a sparse connection
between between between the nodes so i think in this case it would be
better to talk about sets than to talk about graphs and and we
know that we know that transformers are set
neural networks so so in some sense instead of you know looking at you know
a fully connected graph with with uh with feature the thing that
we should look at is more a set of features
and transformers are really good you know to process uh sets
of uh of of feature vectors um okay so so there is a lab um
that i i uh i put here so um the lab is based on um so this is
the gate gcn so the model i'm i i propose and this is
with ggl so this is the deep graph library so it was developed by nyu
shanghai by professor zanzen and uh and and here this is the link to the lab
so if you click on this link you will go directly
to the lab uh and this is this using google google collab so you will just
need a you know a gmail account to access to this and you will be able to
run it on on the google cloud and what i put
here i put really you know the the only the the most interesting uh
functions that you need to develop uh a gcm so uh so so maybe tomorrow uh
yeah tomorrow tomorrow we're gonna be going over everything okay perfect
okay okay so and and here uh i again you know i put some comments
on the code yeah and also yeah also understand dgl
uh how how dga works so probably you do that tomorrow yes yes
nice okay so let me now i'm going to the answer let me talk
a little bit about um benchmarking graph neural networks so recently we
um we have this paper of benchmarking networks so why we did this matchmark
because if you look at you know most published
um gcn papers um most of the work actually
use small data set like a quora rtu data set and only one task the
classification and when i you know when i started doing
some experiment on that i just realized that
if you use gcn or if you don't use an egcn you will get statistically the same
performance because the standard deviation is very
high for the small data sets so so the thing is um we
we cannot identify you know good uh gcm uh we need we need we need something
else and also recently so there has been you
know a new theoretical development for for gcm
and the question is you know how good they are in practice
it's important to to have some good mathematical justification but
you know we need to be able to prove that this is something that is useful
and and i think also benchmark i think very essential to make progress
uh in many fields um like you know of course deep learning with imagenet
by faith lee um but the thing is what i upsell is actually
the people are quite really time to give credit to benchmarks
um anyway so we introduced this open benchmark
infrastructure so it's it's on github and it's based on pi torch
and dgl and we introduced you know six new medium scale data sets
for the four fundamental graph problems like you know graph classification
graph regression not classification and edge classification which i think
if you cover these four fundamental problems you you already
know quite a lot about the performance of your of your gcn
can you spend a few words more about these four fundamental graph problems i
think we haven't mentioned them so far i think yeah um exactly
but but well so what i mentioned is basically the first part of any you know
convolutional nets is how do you extract a powerful feature
the rest is quite easy no if you want to do uh regression you
just use an mlp if you want to do
classification you should use mlp with cross entropy
and the thing i think is is i mean i can take more time to do that but
what i present is i think is more uh you know uh
is more interesting than doing just these these guys
but would you give me another hour we could do that
i was making the point that i i think i understand now how we can build a
basically a representation of a graph but then so you would have like this uh
basically uh feature per node but then how would you go from
this feature per node to the final task so maybe we can mention this such
that we can give someone sure so so what you do basically um
so for example if uh so you have feature exactly so you extract convolutional
features per node and and then suddenly if you want to do
for example graph classification so what you will do you will do some
kind of aggregation you know function on this feature node
so for example the most common one is to do the average
so you do the average of all feature nodes and then on the top of
that you use an mlp and then you will do classification
uh of of your graph and this would be for always the same kind of structure of
the graph or you have different structures like different numbers of
nodes so is it like would you use if you use the mean it's
completely independent of the number of nodes
right right right the same so if you do the sum if you do the max
so you have many operators which are independent of the number of nodes
[Music] and yeah so so we have this and um and
this medium says uh this medium size are actually enough you
know statistically separate the performance of graph neural networks
so we make easy you know for new users to add a new
new graph graph models and also new data sets
and this is this is the link to the to the repo so
let me now explain the graph neural network pipeline
so a standard graph neural network pipeline is composed of three layers
so the first layer is going to be an input layer and it's going to make an
embedding of the input node and edge features then
you will have a series of kraftner network layers and
finally you have a task layer so there will be a
prediction layer for graph node and edge task
let me now describe in details you know each of these three layers
so for the input layer um so again we will have you know the input node and
edge features so this comes from the application that can be you
know a node feature for example for um you know for recommend for
recommender system for products so it will give you you know some feature of
your product so what you will do is that you will
take this um this raw feature and you will make you
know an embedding a linear medium and you will get a vector of d
dimensions we can do the same if we have some edge feature we can do
an embedding of the input edge feature and we'll get a vector of
the dimension so basically the output of the embedding
layer will be um for h it's going to be a matrix
of endnotes and d dimensions for the features
for the edge is going to be a matrix of e the number of edges
times the the number of features and then so we will give that
and we will give you know this output of the embedding layer it's going to be
the input of the graph neural network layers
okay which is which is here then what we will do is that we will
apply our favorite graph normal layer
a number of l times okay so we have um the the node and the edge
representation at layer l it will go through uh the
gnn layer and it will give you node representation of h
and e at the next layer and we will do that you know
l number of times this will give us you know
uh the output of the graph network layers
and again it's going to be a matrix of endnotes and d dimensions
for the nodes and for the edges is going to be a matrix of
e which is the number of edges times the dimensionality
okay so this is the output of our graph and all network layers
and then finally for the last layer so this is
you know task based uh layer so if we if we are doing some prediction at
the graph levels what happened is that we are
going to take you know the the output of the kraftner network
layers and we're going to make a mean with respect to all nodes of the graph
okay so this will give us a representation of the graph
of the dimension then we will give that through to an mlp multi-layer perceptron
and it will give us you know a score which can be a scatter if we are
doing some graph degradation like you know chemical property
estimation or it can be a classification
if we are trying to classify you know molecules to
some classes we can also have you know a nod level
prediction so what we will do is that we will take
the node representation at the output of the graph neural network
and we will give that to an mlp and we will get a score
for the node i which can be a scalar for regression
or can be a k dimensional vector for classification
we can also do you know edge level prediction
so we have a link between node i and node j
uh it's going to be concatenation of the you know the graph neural network uh
representation for node i and not j we give that to an mlp and again we'll
have a score for the link between node i and j and it can be
regression or classification okay so quickly because i'm running out
of time so the task you have the graph
classification task the graph regression path sorry
so this is for molecules so here we want to
predict you know the molecular solubility
and here you have the table so this is like you know
agnostic gcn so we don't use any graph structure
the lower the better and and here this is isotropic
gcn and this is anisotropic gcn so usually you will see
that for most experiments um anisotropic gcn do better job than than
isotropic gcn because you use some of course on
directional property so this is for graph regression this is
for graph classification so you have super nodes
of um of images and you want to classify the the image to belong to one of
the classes uh you also have h classification so this is here the
combinatorial optimization problem of tsp so the traveling salesman problem
so you have a graph and then you want to know if this edge belongs to the
solution so if it belongs to a solution this is
the class one and if it doesn't belong this is class zero
and we see that here you need explicit edge feature so you see that the only
model that does a good job compared to the naive
stick is is by using explicit um edge feature okay so here i'm using i'm
using this combinatorial example to make a
workshop announcement so this is also what we
organizing next year with jan [Music]
organizing a workshop on combining deep learning and combinatory optimization
which i think is very interesting directional research
okay conclusion um so we generalize the covenant to data on
graphs for this we we needed to redesign a
convolution opera operator on graphs so we do that for
template matching which lead to the class of special gcn
we also did that with a spectral convolution which leads to the class
of spectral convolution per spectral gcm we have linear complexity from
real-world graphs we have gpu implementation but yet it's
not optimized for the gpu that we we have today we have universal learning
capacity so this is uh the recent theoretical works
and we can do that for multiple graphs and also for graphs that that that can
change you know dynamically application so i'm happy
that now that i don't need to justify anymore the why
we are doing graph conventional nets to to anybody so it's it's getting more and
more application uh we see that at the nice uh at the
last um actually this week um
iclear uh conference so um the the the keyword that gets you know
the most uh improvement was graph neural networks
and and you can have you know you have now you
know a workshop and tutorials on graphical networks at
many of the top uh deep learning and ai conferences
and this is um the first probably tutorials on graph
deep learning that we we organized at norips in 2017 and cdpr
and also if you want some materials to uh to look more so we have this
ipam workshop um organized in 2018 and also a follow-up
in 2019 and for this we have the video talks so
if you want to know more about this uh so yeah thank michael writer so you
saw banjo michael bronstein felicia monty chattana joshi
uh g willie yo leo thomas lawrence archer slam only michael
duffy are playing earlier so thank you
thank you it was really impressive and i think everyone here was stunned by your
the quality of the slides and your explanations we
really really enjoyed like i'm getting so many private messages here i'm
it's like like everyone's pretty very excited
um i i have actually a few questions if you
have some time left yes um we haven't talked about generative
models um do you have any any words about like how
we can for example generate i don't know like new proteins
for uh i don't know uh figuring out whether
we can find a cure for this kovid right now
just you know actually like how do you say current
question for the current world yeah absolutely so so yeah the community
is also working on the graph generative models so you have two
directions the first direction you can do it in a
recursive way so um what you're going to do is that you
are create you know your molecule atom after atom okay so you create you you
start with an atom then you have a candidate for the next
atom and also the next bound between the two atoms
and you can do that you know it's a kind of lstm style
and the second direction is to do it you know
in uh in one shot so you need um a network that can
that can predict uh what is the length or the size of
your uh of your molecule and then uh
and then what are the connection so you have this two direction you can do it in
a recursive way or you can do it in one shot
so they are they are different um so the community
is more interesting in the recursive way today um
and i i have a paper on the one shot and basically they are they are performing
the same i mean it's uh i don't i don't see any any
difference but you can do it yeah so the only thing
is how do you treat yeah how the question is your molecule
can have different uh size uh and this is the key
um this is the key uh [Music]
i would say the challenge here so how do you deal with different sizes
but we have different options to do that which is very interesting related to the
chemistry of that is that so graph what i want to make is that graph neural
network in some sense are too much flexible
okay so um what you need so when you go from from the standard of
net um so this this as you know the grid is
very structured okay so you can get a lot of information
for the structure of the grid but you don't have this in
graph again you lose you know um the node ordering and
everything so we need to find a way to you know to
have more and more structure inside the graph neural networks
one way to do that is uh the architecture so the architecture for
example you would like to combine uh for example if you do uh chemistry
you would like to combine schroedinger equation
you know like hamilton energy so people are doing that yes to constrain better
you know your graph neural network so again
graphene network are in some sense um you know too much flexible you need to
find a way to to add more um universal you know
constraints yeah actually about the universal
constraints i got here a question uh what do you mean by universal learning
capacity yeah so this is the recent works on
rafale network so people are trained to um
in some sense you're trying to classify your neural networks right there are
many publication neural networks so how do you classify them so you need
to find mathematical properties like you know isotropic properties anisotropic
properties and more recently there are you know
theoretical work on you know isomorphism and you know um
exposibility of craft neural network depending on some class
of of theoretical graphs graphs are you know starting by
earlier like two 200 years ago so we know a lot about graphs
and we want to classify graphs according to some mathematical property
so this is what i was i was trying to mention that
um uh you can you can design graph neural networks
for some special mathematical properties let's see
thank you um guys feel free to ask questions you can
also write to me if you're too shy i mean i'm not shy i can just read
uh i have a question and thank you so much for this great lecture uh and
you mentioned that you created like a benchmark data set
uh type of like uh so people can benchmark their different graph neural
networks um but i i feel like a lot of those
networks also learn some like representation in the graph
and a lot of downstream tasks could be like an unsupervised setting
where i think in the benchmarking data sets you're
all just using accuracy uh more or less so it's like you have labels ground
truth labels so it's more in the supervised setting so
do you have any thoughts on how we could benchmark like the graph network's
performance in an unsupervised setting or i don't know like some
semi-supervised setting um or like by measuring their
performance in some common downstream tasks or application
uh i would like to hear your thoughts on that thank you
so i think this is one of the most favorite uh topics of jan
and the self-supervised yeah that's right uh yeah as you can
tell i brainwashed the students in the class really well
yes yes so that's why i'm asking no of course i mean um of course
one important question um is um you you want to to learn efficiently
right you don't want to have too much labels to be able to
to predict well so so self-supervised learning um
um is is one way to do that right you want to um and you can do that also with
graph right you can you can hide some part of the
information of your graph and then you can predict
this hidden information to get you know a presentation
so um i guess now it's hard for me to follow
uh the recent all the recent gcn work but
i guess if you google it there will probably be already one or two papers on
this on this idea i mean there is nothing special with gcn
so you can apply the same ideas like self-supervised learning
to gcn so we don't we don't put that in the
in the benchmark yet it's a good idea so that's something maybe we
we could do so actually arguably uh all of self-supervised learning
actually exploits some sort of graph structure
right so when you do self-supervised running in text for
example you take you know you take a sequence of words
and you learn uh you know to predict uh a word in the middle of missing words
whatever they are uh there is a graph structure and that graph structure
is uh how many times a word appears uh you know some distance away from
another word so make um you know imagine you have all the
words and then you uh you say you know within this context
you know make a graph between words so this would be a very simplified
version of it but make a graph that indicates
uh how many times this word appears at distance
three from that uh from that other word right
then you have another graph for distance one and another one for distance two etc
right so that constitutes a graph and it's a graph that sort of indicates you
know in white context two words seven simultaneously appear um you can
think of uh uh you know a text as you know
basically a linear graph and you know the the neighbors that you take
uh in a you know when you train a
transformer basically you know sticking a neighborhood in this graph
right so um when you do metric learning uh the type of stuff that is trying
talked about uh you know using contrastive training
where you have two samples that you know are similar and two samples you know are
dissimilar this basically is a graph it's a
similarity graph that you're using you're saying you're telling the system
here are two samples that are linked uh because i know they are similar and
here are two samples that i know are not linked because i know they're dissimilar
and i'm trying to find a graph embedding essentially you can think of
those neural nets are learning a graph embedding for nodes
so that uh nodes that are linked in the graph have similar vectors and
nodes that are not are dissimilar vectors so
there is a very very strong connection between self-supervised running
and uh uh you know kind of the graph view of uh of a training set
i don't think it's been exploited or kind of realized yet
by a lot of people so there might be really interesting stuff to do there i
don't know what you think about this have you but
yeah exactly this is completely related to the you know on the on the graph you
don't have any uh non-positioning and what you are
saying and is exactly that so how do we get you know
positioning between notes that are relevant to your particular application
and and and you want to do it in a self-supervised way
because because then you will learn you know all possible you know
configurations and you don't need to to have labels to do that so yeah this
is the point see you will get if you if you know how to
compare you know um notes so basically how do you extract
positional encoding then you you will do a great job you know
that's that's that's that's one of the most important uh question in graph
neural networks and also for for nlp and many other applications
great thank you a question just arrived here
uh so could you possibly highlight the most important parts of graph
with attention i think we maybe have gone a little fast
there and someone got a little bit lost yeah so uh graph attention network so
the first technique was developed by joshua banjo peter
will actually wix and uh so it's probably you know the first work you you
you would like to see um but you can also do like uh you can
take you know the transformer the standard transformer and then you
can make it you know a graph version it's it's quite straightforward
to do it just by multiplying the just by
multiplying with the urgency agency matrix right yeah exactly
so you can already do it you know with spy
touch transformer so there is a mask exactly with a minus infinity yeah
exactly so if you put minus infinite with soft max you will get zero exactly
so i think i'm gonna show these tomorrow so
they are yeah exactly so you can already do graph you know transformer very
easily with with spy touch but the thing is it's
it's going to be a full matrix yeah so so it's going to take you it's
going to it's going to use a lot of your gm
memory because there are many values that you don't need
so if you if you want to to scale to larger graphs
then you need something that exploits the sparsity like dgn
or python geometric for example yeah so last week we coded by
by from scratch so we we actually see all the operations inside
and then maybe we can just add one additional matrix there just to make
like this masked part such that we can retrieve
the graph convolutional net from the code that we already
have written so that would be i think a connection
for tomorrow and hold on there are more questions coming
is there any application where using chebnet
might be better than spatial gcn um so
i would say they are part of the you know isotropic
um this is the class i uh yeah this is what i call you know isotropic uh gcns
so um uh for me i mean of course it will
depend on your data and you will depend on your task you
know if you have some tasks where your data is uh
you know isotropic this kind of information then chemnet will do a very
good job uh for sure now if you have information
where the topic is important for example for social networks
you don't want you know to treat people the same way the same
you don't want to treat the neighbors the same way then is not going to do a
good job so it really depends on on your task
where isotropy is is very important if isotropic is very important then you
should use net because chemnet you know is using um
all bit of information about your graph in an isotopic way
and if you are using you know gcn the veneer gcn you are just using you know
the first two terms of approximation of gemini
yes it is there we can learn the edges right we can learn the representation
for the edges such that they discriminate between neighbors right
no no no this is um no this is that this one is isotropic
oh okay okay isotropic what i mean by isotropic is that
if um if you have a pure isotropic you know uh graph problems then you
should use a chemical otherwise but otherwise yeah it's better
to use enzotropic of course
more questions guys i'm really um hey i have a question thanks for the talk
uh i was wondering a lot of these methods require
a existing adjacency matrix and for uh some problems for example like you
don't you know that there is a graph structure but you don't know the
underlying connections do you know of any work that addresses
this problem yeah absolutely so um so far most works
uh focus on having already you know the
graph structure and and and of course uh you
like sometimes sometimes you just have data like for example you know you just
have a set of uh set of features and and you want to
learn you know some graph structure it's very hard very very hard
so um there are some works you know doing that
so they are trying to learn some some graph structure at the same time they're
trying to learn you know another presentation uh so
that's that's promising that that's that's interesting
and this is also somewhat that i'm trying to do now but i can tell you
it's very hard to do and especially because um if you
if you if you let you know the adjacency matrix to be a variable
then you are n square okay you have n square
unknown parameters to learn so um so it's uh it's not easy um but yeah this
is a so i would say that these techniques um
there are many natural that are coming with graphs okay you
don't need to build any graphs and this is already giving you you know
a lot of of good tools now if you can give me
maybe what you have in mind what kind of
application you have in mind what you want to use you know when you want to
learn graphs uh at the same time maybe we can talk
about it so i can tell you xavier of course
zimming uh you know will will correct me but
zooming is actually uh working on uh predicting uh protein function predict
uh you know protein function prediction
basically and and so the underlying graph would be the
for example a contact map or the the kind of proximity graph of different
sites on a protein and you don't have that i mean in most
cases you don't that's that's kind of one of the things you
you have to predict so you could view this as some sort of related
you know graph variable let's see maybe you had some other idea
in mind yeah i i think actually so the more specific
problem is that uh some of these graphs you know the edges
and you uh you know some of the edges but you
don't know the other ones for example in protein function prediction
you can imagine like two proteins that have um similar functions as having an
edge between them um but they might not have the same
function so you don't know sort of the edge weights and you kind of have like a
human labels that are inaccurate so uh you know that they're connected in
some way but you don't know the edge weights and you know that
there are other proteins that should be connected but you don't have labels for
so i guess this is more of a graph completion problem yeah and but
and this one is easy this one if you have it's like the semi you know the
semi graph clustering problem so if you
already have some label just a few labels and you have some
structure around this that's something you can you can live
with uh if you are absolutely no structure on the edge
and then you need to learn the graph that is very hard
i see okay thank you hey i have a question about uh
uh splits of the data when you're actually training
a graph neural network um because it's uh
like can you talk about some of the things that you would want to consider
when actually splitting the data into say training and validation
um like you might want to have uh all of the nodes in the training data
for it to actually be exposed to everything that's
um in in the in in the graph data um and you might have a case where
different types of edges are imbalanced in the data set um can you
talk about when that would be important what are some of the considerations in
splitting the data training sorry i'm not sure i understand the
question so you are talking about uh unbalanced training sets uh
yes and also like so if you have like a huge relational
uh data set right um you can talk about some of the
considerations for uh for splitting the data when you're
trying to train a graph network so for a condition on the data sets um
so you may have you know millions of small graphs
and it is fine i mean because this graph neural network they're independent
of the size of your graph so uh so this is this is not issue to learn some
good graphene representation there is no issue with that now
if you have unbalanced data set um i don't know um so that's maybe you can
maybe apply some standard techniques to uh
to do that so uh you can also you know for cross entropy for example you can
you can weight your cross-entropy depending on the size of each class
so that may be something you can do yeah but i
never you know thought too much about this
okay thank you any more questions i'm still getting
things written here but you can voice yourself if you are
i have a question actually uh first of all thanks a lot for the lecture at this
time especially for you so how do you deal with cases where the
nodes do not have the same dimension like if i want to run a small
simple vanilla graph convolutional network but my nodes
are something like even for facebook uh people
and then pages and i want different dimensions so how do you think about
graph like very a very simple graph neural
network in that uh nothing it has nothing to do with
graph neural networks if you have different dimensions for your vector so
probably you need to to to put everything on the same
dimension and then you need to use some indicator function
like one when you have the information and then when you don't have any
information and this will be used during the computation of the loss and
then when you back propagate you if you if you don't have any feature
information you will not use it but i i don't think he has anything to
do with graph neural network okay thank you
hold on you're writing i'm reading so much
so maybe i don't understand the question but i will read it
out loud anyway uh is there any gcn which can work on multiple
urgency matrices together for example a bidirectional graph i don't know what
this mean so if the question is about hyper graph
so you know you may have more than one age uh connecting your nodes yes there
are some work about this it's an extension to natural
extension mathematically so you can yeah you can do that there is
a there is no limitation to go to hyper graph
it's fine and there are now some data sets
for this for this task so if there is a an application
so students would be interesting to do yeah it's there is already
data set and papers okay uh another question would be
does it make sense to have notes that are features of a person
and do graph classification or have notes as person and do
node classification i don't know i don't know um so
often you know people ask me the question can i do a graph given this
data so it's really task dependent i think
it's ready you know when when it's going to be useful or not
when you get you know some good relationships
um because what is the graph you know it's just a collection of pairwise
you know uh or pairwise connections so that's it
so the question is when when it is relevant
to solve your task sometimes it is relevant sometimes it's not
so it really depends on the on the yeah it's obvious but it really depends on
the data and and the task you want to solve so
yeah yeah the student is satisfied with your answer
i think we run out of questions unless there are more
coming my way uh no it's it starts getting bright outside
there exactly exactly it was notice here the
sun is rising uh that's nice okay i think
that was it uh thank you so so much it was like
i mean really those were so pretty uh these slides were so pretty
i i i had to learn so much from the way it teach this world um
yeah thank you again uh for waking up so early
i mean i think this is a fascinating topic you know as you know i've been uh
involved in this at the beginning and uh i think it opens a completely new door
to applications of machine learning and neural nets
you know it's a new world it's completely different world um i know
your phd advisor had been working on you know
graph signal processing for a long time so this was kind of a natural
transition for for him and for you i guess but um
uh i you know i i think we haven't seen the the end of this we'll we'll uh
we're going to be surprised by what's going to come out of this i mean there's
really already sort of fascinating work in that area in high energy physics in
computational chemistry in uh you know social uh
network uh applications and uh you you kind of cited all the big names
in the you know if you are interested in this topic if you're listening to this
yuri leskovitch is is one of the big names you know in addition to xavier
obviously but um and uh jean broner whom you know
because he's a professor here and he talks about it in in this
in this course uh mikhail bronstein uh is also a big contributor he's made some
really interesting uh uh contributions to the to the topic
also on sort of different methods than the one
uh that you talked about today uh on like you know
uh like you know using graph neural nets for like 3d meshes and uh
for computer graphics and things like that so um i
agree i think i think this is also a field you know
where there is a back and forth between you
know mathematics and also applications so if you look at
for example this protein stuff it's very very hard but at the same
times we can learn a lot you know from the mathematical side
we can we can and it's very exciting right because you want both if you want
to be able to make a scientific discovery you need to be
you know um uh driven by some real world very hard problem and then at
the same time you have these new tools you know coming up with a
graphic neural networks and and it's a way also for us to better
understand you know why neural networks work so well
and and this is you know a direction where
it looks like you know each day they are like a new problem in this in this
direction so the pie is big and for everyone for
for the young students to come and to uh to enjoy you know this this area
of research great well thank you again and uh enjoy
your day yeah thanks again thank you so much guys
all right bye-bye bye-bye guys see you tomorrow